I write about food. I write about cooking.
لدي مقالات في مجالي الطعام والطبخ,
I take it quite seriously,
واتعامل مع هذه المواضيع بجدّية.
but I'm here to talk about something
إلا أنني سأتحدث عن شيء مختلف هذه المرة
that's become very important to me in the last year or two.
أمر شغل تفكيري خلال السنة أو السنتين الماضيتين
It is about food, but it's not about cooking, per se.
أمر يتعلق بالغذاء , لكن ليس في مجال طبخ الطعام
I'm going to start with this picture of a beautiful cow.
سأبدء حديثي بصورة لبقرة جميلة.
I'm not a vegetarian -- this is the old Nixon line, right?
"أنا لست نباتياً" ...أحد اقوال الرئيس نيكسون .اليس كذلك؟
But I still think that this --
الا انني مازلت اعتقد بأن هذه البقره
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- may be this year's version of this.
قد تكون الشكل الجديد هذه السنة لهذا ..
Now, that is only a little bit hyperbolic.
الا انه مٌبالغ فيه قليلا.
And why do I say it?
لماذا أقول هذا؟
Because only once before has the fate of individual people
مرّة واحدة فقط كان مصير الفرد
and the fate of all of humanity
ومصير الإنسانية
been so intertwined.
امر متشابك جداً.
There was the bomb, and there's now.
كانت هناك قنبلة، وما تزال موجودة.
And where we go from here is going to determine
وما سنختاره الان هو ما سيحدد
not only the quality and the length of our individual lives,
ليس طول فترة حياة كل فرد منّا ومدى الصحة التي يتمتع بها فحسب,
but whether, if we could see the Earth a century from now,
بل ما إذا كنا سنشهد الأرض بعد قرن من الآن
we'd recognize it.
كما عرفناها من قبل.
It's a holocaust of a different kind,
إنها شكل مختلف للمحرقة،
and hiding under our desks isn't going to help.
و دفن الرؤوس في الرمال لن يفيدنا!
Start with the notion that global warming
ولنبداء بالرأي القائل بأن الاحتباس الحراري ليس امرا واقعيا فحسب,
is not only real, but dangerous.
بل وخطير.
Since every scientist in the world now believes this,
ولأن العلماء حول العالم يؤمنون بهذا الامر,
and even President Bush has seen the light, or pretends to,
حتى الرئيس بوش يؤمن بأنها قضية خطيرة, او ربما يتظاهر بذلك
we can take this is a given.
نحن نعتبر هذا مسلمٌ به.
Then hear this, please.
ارجوا أن تنصتوا لما سأقول,
After energy production, livestock is the second-highest contributor
تعتبر الثروة الحيوانية ثاني اكبر مساهم
to atmosphere-altering gases.
في تغيير الجو بعد انتاج الطاقة.
Nearly one-fifth of all greenhouse gas
فقرابة خُمس ما تطلقة الدفيئة من انبعاثات غازية
is generated by livestock production --
مصدره تربية المواشي !
more than transportation.
اي اكثر مما تطلقه وسائل المواصلات!
Now, you can make all the jokes you want about cow farts,
تستطيعون الان اختلاق عدد لا حصر له من الطرائف حول الغازات التي تطلقها الأبقار
but methane is 20 times more poisonous than CO2,
الميثان غاز أكثر سُمّية من ثاني اكسيد الكربون بعشرين مره
and it's not just methane.
لكن الميثان ليس الخطر الوحيد.
Livestock is also one of the biggest culprits in land degradation,
فتربية المواشي هي السبب الأول في تدهور الأراضي
air and water pollution, water shortages and loss of biodiversity.
تلوث الهواء والماء, و شحّ المياه, وفقدان التنوع البيولوجي.
There's more.
وهنالك المزيد.
Like half the antibiotics in this country
إن نصف المضادات الحيوية في هذا البلد
are not administered to people, but to animals.
تُجرّب على الحيوانات لا على البشر
But lists like this become kind of numbing, so let me just say this:
سرد قوائم كهذه قد يصيب الشخص بنوع من الذهول, لذا دعوني أقول لكم
if you're a progressive,
إن كنت شخصا متحضّر (تقدّمي)
if you're driving a Prius, or you're shopping green,
إذا كانت سيارتك من نوع برايوس, أو كنت ممن يتبضع الخضروات
or you're looking for organic,
أو ممن يبحث عن الطعام العضوي
you should probably be a semi-vegetarian.
فمن المرجِّح أنك شبه نباتيّ
Now, I'm no more anti-cattle than I am anti-atom,
لست مناهضا لتربية الأبقار بقدر مناهضتي لكل ما يتعلق بالذره
but it's all in the way we use these things.
المشكلة في طريقة استخدامنا لهذه الاشياء.
There's another piece of the puzzle,
هنالك جزء من الاحجية تحدثت
which Ann Cooper talked about beautifully yesterday,
عنه آن كوبر بشكل رائع امس
and one you already know.
وانتم تعرفون الآن بأنه
There's no question, none, that so-called lifestyle diseases --
لا وجود لما يعرف بالامراض المتعلقة بأسلوب الحياة,ولا شك في ذلك
diabetes, heart disease, stroke, some cancers --
فالسكريّ ,و امراض القلب , والسكتة الدماغية ,وبعض انواع السرطان
are diseases that are far more prevalent here
امراض تنتشر هنا بشكل كبير
than anywhere in the rest of the world.
مقارنة ببقية دول العالم
And that's the direct result of eating a Western diet.
وهذه هي النتيجة المباشرة من اعتماد النظام الغذائي الغربي
Our demand for meat, dairy and refined carbohydrates --
فنحن نستهلك اللحم و منتجات الالبان والكاربوهايدرات المكرره
the world consumes one billion cans or bottles of Coke a day --
يتناول الناس حول العالم مليار علبة او زجاجة كولا يوميا
our demand for these things, not our need, our want,
اقبالنا عليها-لا حاجتنا لها- وانما رغبتنا في تناولها
drives us to consume way more calories than are good for us.
يدفعنا لاستهلاك سعرات حرارية اكثر مما نحتاج
And those calories are in foods that cause, not prevent, disease.
وهذه السعرات الزائدة في الاطعمه هي ما يسبب الأمراض
Now global warming was unforeseen.
لم يكن الاحتباس الحراري امراً مُتَوَقع
We didn't know that pollution did more than cause bad visibility.
لم نكن نعلم بأن للتلوث تأثيرات سلبية سوى سوء الرؤية
Maybe a few lung diseases here and there,
ربما انتشار بعض امراض الرئة هنا وهناك
but, you know, that's not such a big deal.
لكن الأمر لم يكن خطيرا إلى تلك الدرجة
The current health crisis, however,
ازمة الصحة حاليا
is a little more the work of the evil empire.
هي الى حد ما عمل الامبراطورية الشيطانية
We were told, we were assured,
لقد قيل لنا, بل أُكدَ لنا
that the more meat and dairy and poultry we ate,
كلما تناولنا المزيد من اللحوم ومنتجات الالبان,
the healthier we'd be.
اصبحنا أكثر صحة.
No. Overconsumption of animals, and of course, junk food,
لا. فالاستهلاك المفرط للحيوانات -وبالطبع- الطعام السريع
is the problem, along with our paltry consumption of plants.
هو المشكلة.اضف إلى ذلك,ندرة استهلاكنا للنباتات
Now, there's no time to get into the benefits of eating plants here,
لا مجال للحديث عن فوائد تناول النباتات هنا..
but the evidence is that plants -- and I want to make this clear --
إن جميع الادلة تشير إلى أن النباتات- ولكي يكون الأمر واضحا للجميع-
it's not the ingredients in plants, it's the plants.
لا أتحدث عن ما تحويه النباتات من مكونات,وإنما النباتات نفسها
It's not the beta-carotene, it's the carrot.
لا أتكلم عن مركب (بيتا-كاروتين)* ,بل عن الجزر! *البيتا-كاروتين:مركب عضوي يتواجد في الخضروات
The evidence is very clear that plants promote health.
جيمع الادلة توضح أن النباتات تعزز الصحة
This evidence is overwhelming at this point.
وهذه الأدلة قطعيّة ولا مجال للشك فيها
You eat more plants, you eat less other stuff, you live longer.
كلما اكثرت من اكل النباتات وقللت-بالمقابل- من اكل الاصناف الاخرى من الطعام,عشت لفترة اطول
Not bad.
لا يبدو الامر سيئا
But back to animals and junk food.
لنعد إلى الحيوانات و الطعام غير الصحي
What do they have in common?
ما اوجه الشبة بينها؟
One: we don't need either of them for health.
أولا: لسنا بحاجة لأيٍ منها من أجل الصحة
We don't need animal products,
لا نحتاج للمنتجات الحيوانيّة
and we certainly don't need white bread or Coke.
كما أننا بالتأكيد لسنا بحاجة إلى الخبز الابيض ولا إلى الكولا
Two: both have been marketed heavily,
ثانياً: كلا الصنفين سُوِقا بشكل كبير
creating unnatural demand.
وهذا أوجد طلبا غير طبيعيّ عليهما
We're not born craving Whoppers or Skittles.
نحن لم نولد بحنين هائل أو لاعبي بولينج.
Three: their production has been supported by government agencies
ثالثاً:تدعم الحكومة منتجات هذه الشركات
at the expense of a more health- and Earth-friendly diet.
تحت شعارات مثل من أجل صحة افضل, ونظام غذائي صديق للبيئة !
Now, let's imagine a parallel.
دعونا الآن نتصور الامر من جهة أخرى
Let's pretend that our government supported an oil-based economy,
لنفترض أن الحكومة تدعم اقتصاداَ قائماً على النفط
while discouraging more sustainable forms of energy,
وتعمل على تثبيط تطوير الاشكال المستدامة من الطاقة
knowing all the while that the result would be
مع علمها بأن ماتفعله سيؤدي للتلوث
pollution, war and rising costs.
و الحروب ,و زيادة التكاليف
Incredible, isn't it?
أمر لا يصدق!!! اليس كذلك؟
Yet they do that.
هذا ما يحدث في الواقع !!!
And they do this here. It's the same deal.
يفعلون الشيء ذاته هنا!
The sad thing is, when it comes to diet,
المحزن في الأمر هو أنه عندما يتعلق الموضوع بالحمية الغذائية
is that even when well-intentioned Feds
حتى عندما حاول الفدراليون ذوو النوايا الطيبة
try to do right by us, they fail.
توجيهنا, لم يفلحوا
Either they're outvoted by puppets of agribusiness,
إما لأنهم خسروا أمام أولئك المرتزقة الذين يخدمون التجار في مجال الزراعة
or they are puppets of agribusiness.
و إما أنهم المرتزقة انفسهم!
So, when the USDA finally acknowledged
لذا حين اقرّت وزارة الزراعة اخيرا بأن النباتات
that it was plants, rather than animals, that made people healthy,
هي ما يعزز الصحة,لا اللحوم
they encouraged us, via their overly simplistic food pyramid,
و عن طريق هرمها الغذائي شديد البساطة
to eat five servings of fruits and vegetables a day,
شجعتنا على أكل 5 حبات من الفاكهة والخضار يوميا
along with more carbs.
اضافة الى الكربوهايدرات
What they didn't tell us is that some carbs are better than others,
ومالم يتطرقوا له هو أن بعض النشويات أفضل من بعضها الآخر
and that plants and whole grains
و أنه يجب ان تحل النباتات و الحبوب الكاملة
should be supplanting eating junk food.
محل الأطعمة التي لا تحوي على أي قيمة غذائية
But industry lobbyists would never let that happen.
لكن لن يسمح اصحاب هذه الصناعات بحدوث مثل هذا الامر
And guess what?
واحزروا ماذا بعد؟
Half the people who developed the food pyramid
إن نصف الاشخاص الذين اوجدوا هذا الهرم الغذائي
have ties to agribusiness.
لهم علاقة بالاعمال الزراعية!!!
So, instead of substituting plants for animals,
لذا بدلا من استبدال النباتات واللحوم,
our swollen appetites simply became larger,
بكل بساطة,اصبحت شهيتنا للطعام أكبر
and the most dangerous aspects of them remained unchanged.
وما زالت معظم الجوانب الخطرة فيها كماهي
So-called low-fat diets, so-called low-carb diets --
الانظمة الغذائية منخفضة الدهون, أو الانظمة الغذائية منخفضة الكربوهايدرات..
these are not solutions.
ليست حلولا
But with lots of intelligent people
الحل يكمن في وجود اناس اذكياء
focusing on whether food is organic or local,
يضعون جل تركيزهم على ما اذا كان الطعام عضويا أم محليا
or whether we're being nice to animals,
أو ما اذا كنا نتغامل برحمة و حنكة مع الحيوانات
the most important issues just aren't being addressed.
لم يتم طرح اهم القضايا حتى الان !
Now, don't get me wrong.
لا تفهموني بشكل خاطىء
I like animals,
احب الحيوانات
and I don't think it's just fine to industrialize their production
ولا أرى أنه من العدل استثمار ما تنتجه في مجال الصناعة
and to churn them out like they were wrenches.
ولتحويلها إلى زبد كأنما كانت شدادات.
But there's no way to treat animals well,
ولا سبيل لمعاملتها بصورة جيدة
when you're killing 10 billion of them a year.
حين تقتل 10 مليارات رأس في العام
That's our number. 10 billion.
هذا هو الرقم 10 مليارات
If you strung all of them --
إن قمت مثلا بإرسال كل هذه الحيوانات
chickens, cows, pigs and lambs -- to the moon,
الدجاج, و الأبقار, و الخنازير, و الخراف إلى القمر
they'd go there and back five times, there and back.
فإنها ستملئ المسافة بين القمر والأرض 5 مرات ذهابا وإيابا...ذهابا وإيابا
Now, my math's a little shaky, but this is pretty good,
قد لا تكون حساباتي دقيقة جدا,إلى أنها مفيدة إلى حد ما
and it depends whether a pig is four feet long or five feet long,
لأنها ستتأثر بطول الخنزير فقد يصل طوله إلى أربعة او خمسة أقدام
but you get the idea.
أعتقد ان المغزى قد وصل
That's just the United States.
تلك هي الولايات المتحدة وحدها.
And with our hyper-consumption of those animals
ومع الإستهلاك المحموم لتلك الحيوانات
producing greenhouse gases and heart disease,
التي تنتج غازات الدفيئة وأمراض القلب،
kindness might just be a bit of a red herring.
يكون اللطف مثل الرنجة الحمراء.
Let's get the numbers of the animals we're killing for eating down,
لنأخذ أعداد الحيوانات التي نقتلها من أجل الأكل،
and then we'll worry about being nice to the ones that are left.
عندئذ سنقلق حول كوننا لطيفين تجاه تلك المتبقية.
Another red herring might be exemplified by the word "locavore,"
ربما يتم تمثيل رنجة حمراء أخرى تحت مسمى لوكافور "طعام محلي الصنع"
which was just named word of the year by the New Oxford American Dictionary.
التي تم تسميتها بكلمة العام من قبل معجم أوكسفورد الأمريكي الجديد.
Seriously.
بكل جدية.
And locavore, for those of you who don't know,
ولوكافور لأؤلئك الذين لا يعرفونها،
is someone who eats only locally grown food --
هو أن يأكل الشخص فقط أطعمة محلية الصنع.
which is fine if you live in California,
الامر الجيد إن كنت تعيش في كالفورنيا،
but for the rest of us it's a bit of a sad joke.
لكن لبقية ولايات أمريكا فهو نوع من الهزل الحزين.
Between the official story -- the food pyramid --
قصة بين المسؤولين -- الهرم الغذائي--
and the hip locavore vision,
و ورك رؤية اللوكافور،
you have two versions of how to improve our eating.
تجد نموذجين لكيفية تحسين نظامنا الغذائي.
(Laughter).
(ضحك)
They both get it wrong, though.
وكلاهما فهم الأمر بصورة خاطئة.
The first at least is populist, and the second is elitist.
الأول، أقل جماهيرية، والثاني نخبوي.
How we got to this place is the history of food in the United States.
كيف وصلنا لهذا الدرك هو تاريخ الغذاء في الولايات المتحدة.
And I'm going to go through that,
وسأمر عبر ذلك،
at least the last hundred years or so, very quickly right now.
على الأقل المائة سنة الأخيرة، بسرعة.
A hundred years ago, guess what?
قبل مائة عام، تخيلوا؟
Everyone was a locavore: even New York had pig farms nearby,
كان الجميع لوكافور، حتى نيويورك كان لها مزارع خنازير قريبة
and shipping food all over the place was a ridiculous notion.
وإستيراد الغذاء من كل الأنحاء كانت فكرة سخيفة.
Every family had a cook, usually a mom.
كان لكل أسرة طباخ، في العادة ربة الأسرة (الأم).
And those moms bought and prepared food.
وكانت الأمهات يشترين الطعام ويقمن بتحضيره.
It was like your romantic vision of Europe.
لقد كانت مثل رؤيتنا الرومانسية لأوربا.
Margarine didn't exist.
لم يكن الزبد موجوداً.
In fact, when margarine was invented,
في الواقع، حينما تم إختراع الزبد،
several states passed laws declaring that it had to be dyed pink,
قامت عدة ولايات بتمرير قوانين تعلن أنه يجب أن يكون وردي اللون
so we'd all know that it was a fake.
لذا جميعنا يعرف أنه كان وهميا.
There was no snack food, and until the '20s,
لم تكن هناك وجبات خفيفة، حتى مطلع العشرينات،
until Clarence Birdseye came along, there was no frozen food.
حتى جاء المخترع كلارانس بيردسي، لم يكن هناك طعام مجمد.
There were no restaurant chains.
لم تكن هناك فروع للمطاعم.
There were neighborhood restaurants run by local people,
كانت هناك مطاعم في الأحياء يديرها السكان المحليون،
but none of them would think to open another one.
لكن لم يفكر أيٌ منها بإقامة فرع آخر.
Eating ethnic was unheard of unless you were ethnic.
الوجبات العرقية لم يُسمع بها إلا إذا كنت عرقياً.
And fancy food was entirely French.
وكان الطعام الفاخر هو الفرنسي.
As an aside, those of you who remember
وعلى الهامش، لمن يذكرون
Dan Aykroyd in the 1970s doing Julia Child imitations
دان أيكرويد في السبعينيات يمثّل دور جوليا الطفل
can see where he got the idea of stabbing himself from this fabulous slide.
سيعرفوا من أين أتى بفكرة طعن نفسه بهذه الشريحة الرائعة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Back in those days, before even Julia,
رجوعاً لتلكم الأيام، قبل ظهور جوليا،
back in those days, there was no philosophy of food.
في تلك الأيام لم توجد فلسفة للغذاء.
You just ate.
أنت تأكل فقط.
You didn't claim to be anything.
لا تدعي أنك أي شئ.
There was no marketing. There were no national brands.
لم يكن هناك تسويق. لم توجد علامات وطنية.
Vitamins had not been invented.
لم تخترع الفيتامينات بعد.
There were no health claims, at least not federally sanctioned ones.
لم تكن هناك مشاكل صحية، على الأقل أمراض محظورة فيدرالياً.
Fats, carbs, proteins -- they weren't bad or good, they were food.
الدهون ، والكربوهيدرات ، والبروتينات-- لم تكن سيئة أو جيدة، كانت مجرد طعام.
You ate food.
أنت تأكل الطعام فقط.
Hardly anything contained more than one ingredient,
لا يكاد يحوي أي شئ أكثر من مكوّن واحد،
because it was an ingredient.
لأنه لم يكن مكوّن.
The cornflake hadn't been invented.
لم يكن الكورن فليك قد أبتكر بعد.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The Pop-Tart, the Pringle, Cheez Whiz, none of that stuff.
الحبوب اللاذعة ، برينغل ، جبن الأزيز ،لم يوجد أي من هذه الأشياء.
Goldfish swam.
السمكة الذهبية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's hard to imagine. People grew food, and they ate food.
من الصعب التخيّل. زرع الناس الغذاء، وأكلوا الطعام.
And again, everyone ate local.
ومجدداً أكل الجميع الأطعمة المحلية.
In New York, an orange was a common Christmas present,
في نيويورك، كان البرتقال هدية عيد الميلاد الشائعة،
because it came all the way from Florida.
لأنها تأتي من فلوريدا البعيدة.
From the '30s on, road systems expanded,
ومنذ الثلاثينات، توسعت الطرق،
trucks took the place of railroads,
أحتلت الشاحنات مكان القطارات،
fresh food began to travel more.
أصبح الطعام الطازج يسافر لأماكن بعيدة.
Oranges became common in New York.
أصبح البرتقال شائعاً في نيويورك
The South and West became agricultural hubs,
أصبح الجنوب والغرب محاور زراعية،
and in other parts of the country, suburbs took over farmland.
وفي أجزاء أخرى من البلاد أمتدت الضواحي على الأراضي الزراعية.
The effects of this are well known. They are everywhere.
وأثر ذلك معلوم بالضرورة، إنها في كل مكان.
And the death of family farms is part of this puzzle,
وموت المزارع الأسرية هو جزء من هذا اللغز
as is almost everything
مثل كل شئ
from the demise of the real community
من زوال المجتمع الحقيقي
to the challenge of finding a good tomato, even in summer.
لتحدي العثور على طماطم جيدة، حتى خلال فصل الصيف.
Eventually, California produced too much food to ship fresh,
في نهاية المطاف أنتجت كالفورنيا الكثير من الطعام الطازج،
so it became critical to market canned and frozen foods.
وعليه أصبحت مهمة للأطعمة المعلبة والمجمدة.
Thus arrived convenience.
ولذا جاءت الراحة.
It was sold to proto-feminist housewives
تم ترويجها لربات المنازل "الحركة النسوية"
as a way to cut down on housework.
كوسيلة لتقليل الأعباء المنزلية.
Now, I know everybody over the age of, like 45 --
الآن أنا أعرف أن أي شخص فوق عمر 45 --
their mouths are watering at this point.
يسيل لعابهم في هذه النقطة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
If we had a slide of Salisbury steak, even more so, right?
إذا كان لدينا شريحة من شرائح اللحم سالزبوري ، أو أكثر، صحيح؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But this may have cut down on housework,
لكن هذا ربما قلل من الأعباء المنزلية،
but it cut down on the variety of food we ate as well.
لكنه قلل التنوع الغذائي للطعام الذي أكلناها ايضاً.
Many of us grew up never eating a fresh vegetable
ترعرع الكثيرون منا بدون أن يأكلوا أطعمة طازجة
except the occasional raw carrot or maybe an odd lettuce salad.
بإستثناء أكل الجزر أحياناً أو ربما سلطة الخس.
I, for one -- and I'm not kidding --
أنا مثلاً -- وأنا لا أمزح--
didn't eat real spinach or broccoli till I was 19.
لم أتناول سبانخ أو البروكلي طبيعي حتى بلغت 19 عاماً.
Who needed it though? Meat was everywhere.
من يحتاجه في الأساس؟ كانت اللحوم في كل مكان.
What could be easier, more filling or healthier for your family
ما الأسهل، شبع أكثر أم صحة أكثر لأسرتك
than broiling a steak?
من شواء شريحة الستيك؟
But by then cattle were already raised unnaturally.
لكن في ذاك الحين كانت المواشي تُربى بطريقة غير طبيعية بالفعل.
Rather than spending their lives eating grass,
بدلاً عن قضاء وقتها في أكل الأعشاب الطبيعية،
for which their stomachs were designed,
التي تقوم معدتها بهضمها،
they were forced to eat soy and corn.
تم إجبار المواشي على أكل الصويا والذرة.
They have trouble digesting those grains, of course,
ولدى الماشية مشكلة في هضم هذه الحبوب بالطبع،
but that wasn't a problem for producers.
لكن هذه لم تكن مشكلة للمنتجين.
New drugs kept them healthy.
العقاقير الحديثة أبقت على الماشية بصحة جيدة.
Well, they kept them alive.
بصورة أدق، أبقت الماشية على قيد الحياة.
Healthy was another story.
بصحة وعافية هي قصة أخرى.
Thanks to farm subsidies,
بفضل الإعانات الزراعية،
the fine collaboration between agribusiness and Congress,
التعاون الجيد ما بين الأعمال الزراعية التجارية والكونغرس،
soy, corn and cattle became king.
الصويا، الذرة والماشية أصبحت الملك.
And chicken soon joined them on the throne.
وسرعان ما لحق بهم الدجاج على العرش.
It was during this period that the cycle of
في تلك الحقبة بدأت دورة
dietary and planetary destruction began,
الدمار للغذاء والكوكب،
the thing we're only realizing just now.
الشئ الذي ندركه الآن فقط.
Listen to this,
إستمعوا لهذا،
between 1950 and 2000, the world's population doubled.
بين عامي 1950 و 2000، تضاعف عدد سكان العالم.
Meat consumption increased five-fold.
إزداد إستهلاك اللحوم لخمسة أضعاف.
Now, someone had to eat all that stuff, so we got fast food.
الآن، يجب أن يأكل شخص ما .. كل هذه الأشياء، حتى وصلنا للوجبات سريعة.
And this took care of the situation resoundingly.
وهذا ما جعل الحال أكثر سوءا.
Home cooking remained the norm, but its quality was down the tubes.
ظلّ إعداد الطعام منزلياً هو العادة، لكن جودته كانت في الحضيض.
There were fewer meals with home-cooked breads, desserts and soups,
كانت هناك وجبات أقل مع رغيف، حساء وحلويات مصنوعة منزلياً،
because all of them could be bought at any store.
لأن جميعها يمكن شراؤه من المتجر.
Not that they were any good, but they were there.
لم تكن هي الأفضل، لكنها متاحة ومتوفرة.
Most moms cooked like mine:
معظم الامهات طبخن مثل طبخي --
a piece of broiled meat, a quickly made salad with bottled dressing,
قطعة لحم مشوية ، وسلطة معدة بسرعة مع ملفوف معلّب،
canned soup, canned fruit salad.
حساء معبأ، وسلطة فواكه معبأة.
Maybe baked or mashed potatoes,
وربما خبز أو بطاطا مهروسة
or perhaps the stupidest food ever, Minute Rice.
أو ربما أغبى أنواع الأطعمة على الإطلاق -- أرز "مينيت".
For dessert, store-bought ice cream or cookies.
وللصحراء، الكعك المشترى من المتجر أو الآيس كريم.
My mom is not here, so I can say this now.
أمي ليست هنا، لذا يمكنني قول هذا الآن.
This kind of cooking drove me to learn how to cook for myself.
هذا النوع من الطبخ هو ما جعلني أتعلم الطبخ بنفسي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It wasn't all bad.
لم يكن كله سيئ.
By the '70s, forward-thinking people
لكن في السبعينات، بدأ التقدميون
began to recognize the value of local ingredients.
بإدراك قيمة المكونات المحلية.
We tended gardens, we became interested in organic food,
لقد مِلنا للحدائق، وأصبحنا مهتمين بالغذاء العضوي،
we knew or we were vegetarians.
لقد عرفنا أننا كنا نباتيون.
We weren't all hippies, either.
لكننا لم نكن جميعاً "هيبيس" (ثقافة أمريكية فرعية ظهرت في الستينيات)
Some of us were eating in good restaurants and learning how to cook well.
كان بعضنا يأكل في المطاعم الجيدة ويتعلمون كيف يطبخون أيضاً.
Meanwhile, food production had become industrial. Industrial.
في هذه الأثناء، بدأ إنتاج الطعام يأخذ شكلاً صناعياً.
Perhaps because it was being produced rationally,
ربما لأنه كان ينتج بصورة عقلانية
as if it were plastic,
كما لو أنه كان بلاستيكاً،
food gained magical or poisonous powers, or both.
أكتسب الغذاء قوى سحرية أو سُمّية، أو كلاهما.
Many people became fat-phobic.
أصبح الكثير من الناس خائفاً من السُمنة.
Others worshiped broccoli, as if it were God-like.
وعبد آخرون الكرنب كما لو أنه إله.
But mostly they didn't eat broccoli.
لكن في الغالب لم يأكلوا الكرنب.
Instead they were sold on yogurt,
عوضاً أبتاعوا الزبادي،
yogurt being almost as good as broccoli.
أصبح الزبادي تقريباً جيد مثل الكرنب.
Except, in reality, the way the industry sold yogurt
بإستثناء، أن الصناعات سوّقت للزبادي ليباع
was to convert it to something much more akin to ice cream.
محوّلاً لشئ أشبه بكثير بالآيس كريم.
Similarly, let's look at a granola bar.
بالمثل، لننظر لحانة غرانولا.
You think that that might be healthy food,
تعتقدون أن ذلك ربما يكون طعاماً صحياً،
but in fact, if you look at the ingredient list,
لكن في الحقيقة، إذا أمعنتم النظر في قائمة المكونات،
it's closer in form to a Snickers than it is to oatmeal.
فانها شكل مقرب لسنيكرز فضلاً عن دقيق الشوفان.
Sadly, it was at this time that the family dinner was put in a coma,
بكل أسف، في ذلك الوقت كان العشاء المنزلي الأسري قد تضاءل دوره،
if not actually killed --
إن لم يكن قد أنتهى بالفعل.
the beginning of the heyday of value-added food,
بداية ذروة من المواد الغذائية ذات القيمة المضافة ،
which contained as many soy and corn products
التي تحوي الكثير من منتجات الصويا والذرة
as could be crammed into it.
كما يمكن إضافتها.
Think of the frozen chicken nugget.
فكروا بلحم الدجاج المجمد.
The chicken is fed corn, and then its meat is ground up,
يأكل الدجاج الذرة، وينمو لحمه
and mixed with more corn products to add bulk and binder,
ويتم خلطه بالمزيد من منتجات الذرة ليضيفها بالجملة،
and then it's fried in corn oil.
ثم يتم قليها بزيت الذرة.
All you do is nuke it. What could be better?
كل ما تفعله هو طهيها. ما الأفضل من ذلك؟
And zapped horribly, pathetically.
والتخلص منها بفظاعة.
By the '70s, home cooking was in such a sad state
بحلول السبعينيات، كان الطبخ في المنزل في أسوء أوقاته
that the high fat and spice contents of foods
بحيث الدهون الكثيرة والمحتويات الحارة من الأطعمة
like McNuggets and Hot Pockets --
مثل شرائح الدجاج واللفافات الحارة--
and we all have our favorites, actually --
ولدى الجميع ما يفضلونه منها--
made this stuff more appealing than the bland things
جعل هذه الأشياء أكثر جاذبية من الأشياء اللطيفة
that people were serving at home.
التي كان يأكلها الناس في المنزل.
At the same time, masses of women were entering the workforce,
في نفس الوقت، كانت أعداد كبيرة من النساء يدخلون سوق العمل،
and cooking simply wasn't important enough
ولم يعد الطبخ مهماً بما يكفي
for men to share the burden.
وعلى الرجال المشاركة في الأعباء المنزلية.
So now, you've got your pizza nights, you've got your microwave nights,
فقد أصبح الآن لديكم ليالي البيتزا، وليالي المايكروويف،
you've got your grazing nights,
وليالي الأُنس،
you've got your fend-for-yourself nights and so on.
وليالي إعالة نفسك وهلم جرا.
Leading the way -- what's leading the way?
مالذي يقود الطريق إلى ذلك؟
Meat, junk food, cheese:
اللحم، الوجبات السريعة، الجبن.
the very stuff that will kill you.
الأشياء التي تقوم بقتلك.
So, now we clamor for organic food.
لذا الآن نحدث ضجة للأغذية العضوية.
That's good.
ذلك جيد.
And as evidence that things can actually change,
وهو دليل على أن الأشياء يمكن أن تتغير،
you can now find organic food in supermarkets,
يمكن الآن العثور على غذاء عضوي في محلات البقالة،
and even in fast-food outlets.
وحتى في متاجر الوجبات السريعة.
But organic food isn't the answer either,
لكن حتى الغذاء العضوي ليس هو الإجابة
at least not the way it's currently defined.
على الأقل بالطريقة التي يتم تعريفه بها حالياً.
Let me pose you a question.
دعوني أطرح عليكم سؤالا
Can farm-raised salmon be organic,
هل من الممكن أن يُعتبر السلمون المُربى في مزارع طعاما عضويا؟
when its feed has nothing to do with its natural diet,
في حين أن تغذيته تعتمد على طعام غير طبيعي!
even if the feed itself is supposedly organic, and the fish themselves
حتى إذا أفترضنا أن الطعام نفسه عضوياً، وأن الأسماك
are packed tightly in pens, swimming in their own filth?
تم تعبئتها بحذر في لفافات، أتسبح في قذارتها الخاصة؟
And if that salmon's from Chile, and it's killed down there
وإن كان السلمون من تشيلي وتم صيدها هناك
and then flown 5,000 miles, whatever,
ثم انتقلت 5،000 ميلاً،
dumping how much carbon into the atmosphere?
كم تلوّث الغلاف الجوي بالكربون؟
I don't know.
لا اعرف.
Packed in Styrofoam, of course,
تتم عملية التعبة في الستايروفوم بالطبع
before landing somewhere in the United States,
قبل ان تشحن الى مكان ما في الولايات المتحدة
and then being trucked a few hundred more miles.
ثم تقطع مئات الاميال لنقلها الى وجهتها
This may be organic in letter, but it's surely not organic in spirit.
قد تكون هذه الاسماك عضوية شكليا,لكنها ليست كذلك
Now here is where we all meet.
الآن ها هنا حيث نلتقي جميعنا.
The locavores, the organivores, the vegetarians,
اللوكافريون، العضويون،
the vegans, the gourmets
النباتيون، الذواقون
and those of us who are just plain interested in good food.
ومن هم مهتمون بأكل طعام جيد فقط.
Even though we've come to this from different points,
رغماً عن أننا جئنا من خلفيات مختلفة،
we all have to act on our knowledge
يجب علىينا جميعا أن نفعل شيئا كلا حسب علمه
to change the way that everyone thinks about food.
لتغيير الطريقة التي يفكر بها الجميع حيال الغذاء.
We need to start acting.
يجب ان نتحرك
And this is not only an issue of social justice, as Ann Cooper said --
وهذه قضية محورها العدالة الإجتماعية، كما قالت آن كوبر--
and, of course, she's completely right --
وبالطبع هي محقاً تماماً--
but it's also one of global survival.
لكنها أيضاً قضية نجاة كونية.
Which bring me full circle and points directly to the core issue,
الذي يعطيني دائرة مكتملة ونقاط مباشرة للب القضية،
the overproduction and overconsumption of meat and junk food.
الإنتاج الزائد والإستهلاك المفرط للحوم والوجبات السريعة.
As I said, 18 percent of greenhouse gases
كما قلت، 18% من غازات الدفيئة
are attributed to livestock production.
مصدرها تربية المواشي.
How much livestock do you need to produce this?
كم من المواشي تحتاجه لإنتاج هذا الرقم؟
70 percent of the agricultural land on Earth,
70% من الأراضي الزراعية على كوكب الأرض.
30 percent of the Earth's land surface is directly or indirectly devoted
30% من الأراضي المسطحة مكرسة بطريقة مباشرة أو غير مباشرة
to raising the animals we'll eat.
لتربية الحيوانات التي سنأكلها.
And this amount is predicted to double in the next 40 years or so.
ويتوقع أن تتضاعف هذه الكمية خلال ال40 عاماً القادمة.
And if the numbers coming in from China
وإن كانت الأرقام التي تأتي من الصين
are anything like what they look like now,
مثل أي شئ كما تبدو الآن،
it's not going to be 40 years.
فلن يستغرق الأمر 40 عاماً.
There is no good reason for eating as much meat as we do.
ليس هناك سبب وجيه لأكل كمية اللحوم الكثيرة التي نأكلها.
And I say this as a man who has eaten a fair share of corned beef in his life.
وأنا أقول هذا كرجل قد أكل نصيباً وافراً من اللحوم المحفوظة خلال حياتي.
The most common argument is that we need nutrients --
الحجة الشائعة جداً هي أننا بحاجة للمواد الغذائية--
even though we eat, on average, twice as much protein
رغماً عن أننا نأكل بروتينات في المتوسط تعادل ضعفين
as even the industry-obsessed USDA recommends.
مما أوصت به وزارة الزراعة الأمريكية المهووسة بالتصنيع.
But listen: experts who are serious about disease reduction
لكن أسمعوا-- الخبراء الجادون بشأن الحد من الأمراض
recommend that adults eat just over half a pound of meat per week.
يوصون بأن يأكل الشخص البالغ نصف رطل من اللحم أسبوعياً فقط.
What do you think we eat per day? Half a pound.
ماذا تظنون أننا نأكل يومياً؟ نصف رطل.
But don't we need meat to be big and strong?
لكننا ألا نريد اللحوم لنصبح أكبر أو أقوى؟
Isn't meat eating essential to health?
أليس أكل اللحم أساسي للصحة؟
Won't a diet heavy in fruit and vegetables
أليس الطعام الغني بالفواكهة والخضروات
turn us into godless, sissy, liberals?
سيحولنا إلى ليبراليين، مخنثين، ملحدين؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Some of us might think that would be a good thing.
قد يعتقد بعضنا أن هذا سيكون شيئاً جيداً.
But, no, even if we were all steroid-filled football players,
لكن، لا، حتى إن كنت لاعب كرة قدم ضخم بالغازات،
the answer is no.
فالإجابة هي لا.
In fact, there's no diet on Earth that meets
في الواقع، لا يوجد نظام غذائي على الأرض يوفي
basic nutritional needs that won't promote growth,
بالإحتياجات الغذائية الأساسية ولا يعزز النمو،
and many will make you much healthier than ours does.
والكثير سيجعلك أكثر صحة مما عليه أطعمتنا.
We don't eat animal products for sufficient nutrition,
نحن لا نأكل المنتجات الحيوانية لتغذية كافية،
we eat them to have an odd form of malnutrition, and it's killing us.
نحن نأكلها لنصاب بشكل سيئ من سوء التغذية، وهي تقتلنا.
To suggest that in the interests of personal and human health
إقتراح للمصلحة الشخصية والعامة والصحة البشرية
Americans eat 50 percent less meat --
أن يأكل الأمريكيون 50% لحوم أقل --
it's not enough of a cut, but it's a start.
إنه ليس تقليلاً كافياً، لكنها بداية.
It would seem absurd, but that's exactly what should happen,
قد يبدو الامر عبثياً، لكنه ما يُفترض أن يحدث بالضبط،
and what progressive people, forward-thinking people
وما ينبغي أن يكون التقدميون والمتحضرون
should be doing and advocating,
يفعلونه ويروجون له،
along with the corresponding increase in the consumption of plants.
تماشيا مع الدعوة لتناول النباتات.
I've been writing about food more or less omnivorously --
لقد كنت أكتب عن الطعام بشكل ملتهم --
one might say indiscriminately -- for about 30 years.
يمكن للمرء أن يقول دون تمييز-- لحوالي 30 عاماً.
During that time, I've eaten
خلال هذه الفترة أكلت
and recommended eating just about everything.
ونصحت بأكل أطعمة في كل شئ.
I'll never stop eating animals, I'm sure,
لن اتوقف عن تناول اللحوم,وأنا على يقين من هذا
but I do think that for the benefit of everyone,
لكنني أعتقد بأنه من أجل تحقيق مصلحة الجميع
the time has come to stop raising them industrially
علينا التوقف عن تربية الحيوانات لأهداف صناعية
and stop eating them thoughtlessly.
,و أكلها بدون تفكير
Ann Cooper's right.
آن كوبر على صواب فيما قالته
The USDA is not our ally here.
وزارة الزراعة الأمريكية ليست حليفنا
We have to take matters into our own hands,
يجب علينا تولي الأمر بأنفسنا
not only by advocating for a better diet for everyone --
ليس عن طريق حث الناس على اتباع نظام غذائي جيد
and that's the hard part -- but by improving our own.
وهو الجزء الاصعب-وأنما
And that happens to be quite easy.
والأمر سهل جدا
Less meat, less junk, more plants.
قلل من اللحم و الوجبات السريعه,و أكثر من الخضروات
It's a simple formula: eat food.
إنها معادلة بسيطة..تناول طعاما
Eat real food.
طعام حقيقي
We can continue to enjoy our food, and we continue to eat well,
يمكننا الاستمتاع وتناول طعام صحيّ في وقتٍ واحد
and we can eat even better.
بإمكاننا أن نتغذى بشكل أفضل
We can continue the search for the ingredients we love,
يمكننا مواصلة البحث عن المكونات التي نحب،
and we can continue to spin yarns about our favorite meals.
ويمكننا مواصلة الدوران حول وجباتنا المفضلة.
We'll reduce not only calories, but our carbon footprint.
سنقوم بتقليل ليس فقط السعرات الحرارية، بل بصمة التلوث الكربوني خاصتنا.
We can make food more important, not less,
بأمكاننا جعل الطعام اكثر اهمية، ليس أقل أهمية
and save ourselves by doing so.
وننقذ أنفسنا بفعل ذلك.
We have to choose that path.
يجب أن نختار ذلك المسار.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم